Okay, today's דף daf is גיטין Gittin נה, nun hey, 55, and
we pick up at the משנה mishna and we're still in the
middle of discussions around things that are done for תיקון העולם tikkun
ha-olam or similar types of תקנות. takkanot. העיד Heid רבי יוחנן בן
גודגדא. Rabbi Yochanan ben Gudguda. We pick up with the משנה. mishna.
רבי יוחנן בן גודגדא Rabbi Yochanan ben Gudguda testified to the following
tradition. This is a משנה mishna that's also in עדיות. Eduyos. עדיות
Eduyos is a מסכת masechet which is a collection of testimonies different
people had of halachic traditions, and רבי יוחנן בן גודגדא Rabbi Yochanan
ben Gudguda testified to the following tradition: על חרשת שהשיאה אביה, al
chereshet shehishia aviha, if you have a girl who was a deaf
deaf and not able to speak intelligibly, normally we say חרשת chereshet
is deaf mute, but it doesn't mean literally can't speak, it just
means that because they were born deaf, never able to learn how
to speak in a way that hearing people, like in a way
that was intelligible. So that person halachically is considered to be an
אינו בר דעת, eino bar da'as, somebody who does not have sufficient
intellect to be obligated in מצוות mitzvos and to be mean that
their legal transactions would be binding and so on. This has to
do with the fact that until a few hundred years ago when
they figured out how to educate the deaf and they developed schools
for the deaf, the general belief was was that deaf people did
not have the same intellect, proof being that they could not understand
what we were saying and they would not as educated and could
not communicate well and therefore they would act in strange ways. Obviously
all of that had to do with the fact
that society did not yet figure out how to be able to
educate them and develop sign language and so on. So הלכה halacha
assumes that and and that assumption got sort of reassessed very seriously
over the last few hundred years, but obviously that's the assumption that
this משנה mishna is working with. So here's a girl and she
is a חרשת, chereshet, so two reasons why she's not yet doesn't
have yet her own ability to transact, but as an underage girl
her father is able to marry her off. So her father marries
her off and the purpose of saying that that was the case
even though the rabbis allowed a חרש cheresh and a חרשת chereshet
they created a rabbinic type of a marriage for somebody who was
either the man or the woman or both were were deaf and
unable to speak intelligibly, but this is a דאורייתא de'oraisa marriage because
the father is able to marry off his daughter when she is
a minor and therefore it is דאורייתא de'oraisa binding. And nevertheless even
though it's דאורייתא de'oraisa binding, she יוצאה בגט. yotzei beget. Now the
husband wants to divorce her, gives her a גט, get, so and
and to give her this גט, get, you might think, well, she
does not have, we we assume she doesn't have דעת, da'as, and
therefore she's not aware about what the giving of the גט get
means, and therefore the giving of the גט get should not work,
and he is testifying that no, the giving of the גט get
does work. Why? Because since a woman can be divorced against her
will, she can also be divorced even if she is not fully
cognizant of what is happening, and that's quite surprising, though you could,
you know, one does not necessarily mean the other, but that is
the position that הלכה halacha adopted and that allowed her to be
divorced. ועל קטנה בת ישראל שנישאת לכהן, ve'al ketana bas yisrael shenises
lechohen, so that's teaching number one, very relevant to גיטין, Gittin, but
we'll see all of these testimonies of רבי יוחנן בן גודגדא Rabbi
Yochanan ben Gudguda really said because of the ends which are certain
types of תקנות. takkanot. ועל קטנה בת ישראל שנישאת לכהן. ve'al ketana
bas yisrael shenises lechohen.
Now if you have a a minor girl who is married to
a כהן kohen and not married by her father, so this is
only a דרבנן derabbanan marriage because there was a need for to
protect the interests of of women and of daughters in a society
in which you know they could not would not generally earn for
themselves and be able to protect themselves. Even when the father was
not around, the rabbis saw the need to establish a a way
in which she could be married through her by her mothers and
brothers, but that קידושי קטנה, kiddushei ketana, that is a דרבנן, derabbanan,
that's not דאורייתא. de'oraisa. So here she was and she was married
to a כהן, kohen, so this is not binding from the Torah,
and a כהן, kohen, his wife and his children can eat תרומה,
terumah, which is normally forbidden to non-כוהנים, kohanim, his children of course
are כוהנים, kohanim, but his wife is not, and nevertheless since she's
married to a כהן, kohen, she is able to eat תרומה. terumah.
So here even though the marriage is only דרבנן, derabbanan, nevertheless אוכלת
בתרומה, ocheles biterumah, they allowed her to eat תרומה, terumah, and we'll
see why that is in the גמרא. gemara. Obviously that gives more
weight to the idea that this is a real marriage and it
might have been very hard to manage without that, there he is
eating תרומה terumah at the whole table and she has to avoid
it and so on, but how they are able to do that
given it's not a דאורייתא de'oraisa marriage we'll see in the גמרא.
gemara. ואם מתה בעלה יורשה, ve'im mesa ba'ala yorshah, and if she
dies her husband inherits her, that's another הלכה halacha not limited to
a כהן kohen that even though קידושי קטנה kiddushei ketana is only
rabbinic, it would follow the same Torah law, the same law as
if it was a Torah marriage where the husband inherits the wife
on her death. Okay. ועל המריש הגזול שבנאו בבירה שיטול את דמיו,
ve'al hamarish hagazul shebna'o bebira sheyitol es damo, and on a beam
that was stolen that was built into a castle, somebody stole, you
know, imagine a
a concrete brick, a cornerstone and laid it at the foundation of
a building and then built the entire building and you can still
see it, look at the brick is right there, the cornerstone is
right there, it's still mine you have to give it back to
me. So halachically if It's still the owners' and it can still
be identified, then it has, the owner has a right to return
it. You know, there's questions about a שינוי, shinui, about how much
of a change transforms it and it's no longer the owner can
claim it. But in some circumstances, you know, it might be really,
you know, like like like deep in the building, but technically it
hasn't really changed. It's still the same beam or the brick that
it used to be. And now the question is, is that can
the owner demand it back? So the הלכה halacha was no, שקניתהו
shekinitahu סתמא stama that we said that the owner just you just
pay the owner the money, you don't actually have to go ahead
and return the beam itself, משום תקנת השבים. Mishum takanas hashavim,
And here we get the תקנה takkanah language because of the תקנה
takkanah of we want to help people do תשובה teshuva and we
want people to own up to their, you know, to their thefts
and so on and therefore we do not want this to be
an obstacle. וחטאת הגזולה vechatat hagzulah שלא נודעה לרבים shelo nodah larabim
and a stolen sin offering that was not known to the to
the masses, meaning it was not public knowledge that this sin offering
was stolen. So Reuven stole Shimon's חטאת chatat and then wanted to
bring it to offer it up for his own sacrifice, or another
possibility we'll see which of these is true in the גמרא. Gemara.
The other way is he just stole Shimon's cow and he sanctified
it. So here you have that's really the case in the גמרא
Gemara as we'll see. Okay, so you have a you have this
animal that was stolen and is now being used and has been
sanctified by Shimon, excuse me, I forget who's who. Anyway, Reuven stole
Shimon's non-sanctified animal, Reuven sanctified it, he wants to bring it as
a קרבן. korban. If it's if it's not known that it's stolen,
then שהיא מכפרת shehi mechaperet nevertheless we will allow it to atone
מפני תיקון המזבח mipnei tikkun hamizbeach for the sake of a תקנה
takkanah for the sake of the מזבח. mizbeach. Okay, of the altar.
Now what exactly תיקון מזבח tikkun mizbeach there is here and whether
the real הלכה halacha should be it should always work, it should
always not work, what exactly is the distinction between well-known or not
well-known, we will see this in the גמרא. Gemara.
I should mention that these four things, you know, they seem a
little bit random, they might just be the four things that he
had to testify, but there's also if you think about the oral
tradition and the way to remember, there's a way in which these
four things one leads into the next. The first case is השיא
אביה, hisia aviha, her father married her off, this חרשת, chereshet, this
woman, this child who is deaf. And then the next case was
בת ישראל שניסת לכהן, bat yisrael sheniset l'kohen, השיא אביה ניסת לכהן.
hisia aviha niset l'kohen. And then you have בעלה יורשה ba'alah yorshah
inherits her, and המריש הגזול, hamarish hagazul, right, the מריש marish which
is stolen. And then you have חטאת הגזולה שלא נודעה לרבים. chatat
hagzulah shelo nodah larabim. So there's a way in which, you know,
one of these sort of links into the next and you can
remember all of them. Okay, let's take a look at the גמרא.
Gemara. אמר רבא, amar Rava, says Rava, מעדותו של רבי יוחנן בן
גודגדא, meeduto shel Rabbi Yochanan ben Gudgada, from the testimony of Rabbi
Yochanan ben Gudgada we can infer the following הלכה. halacha.
אמר לעדים, amar l'edim, a man said to witnesses, ראו גט זה
שאני נותן לה, reu get zeh she'ani noten lah, see this גט
get here, take a look, read it, you see it's a גט
get and so on, fine, I'm folding it up, I'm going to
give my wife this גט, get, you'll be witnesses that I've delivered
this גט get to my wife. וחזר ואמר לה קנסי שטר חוב
זה, vechazar ve'amar lah kinsi shtar chov zeh, and he said to
her, oh here, take this, you know, could you go ahead and
please take my you know this document of mine, this file folder
or you know this שטר חוב, shtar chov, this promise, this note,
this debtor's note that I have against somebody. Will you go ahead
and take this? And he handed it to her. And he didn't
tell her that it was a גט. get. And then she opened
it up and she saw it was a גט. get. And he
said, ha, surprise, you're divorced. So the הלכה halacha is הרי זו
מגורשת, harei zo megureshet, that actually works even though she was not
aware of what she was taking, the fact that he gave it
to her and she took possession of it, and we'll have to
see later in the מסכת masechet how do you take possession and
so on, that is
enough. כי מי לא אמר רבי יוחנן בן גודגדא לא בעינן דעתה,
ki mi lo amar Rabbi Yochanan ben Gudgada lo bainan da'atah, the
same way Rabbi Yochanan ben Gudgada says that if this person is
a חרשת chereshet is a deaf and therefore we assume she doesn't
have full awareness of what's happening and nevertheless it works, and that
הלכה halacha is learned out from the fact that it could be
against her will, again, against her will does not necessarily mean against
her cognizance or full awareness, but that nevertheless is the tradition, that's
the הלכה. halacha. So once we've established that not only do you
not need her will, but you don't even need her real full
cognizance, הכא נמי לא בעינן דעתה, hacha nami lo bainan da'atah, here
too you don't need her full cognizance and as long as, you
know, she's aware that she's getting some piece of paper and she's
taking possession of it, that's enough.
פשיטא, peshita, well that's obvious, meaning okay, maybe Rabbi Yochanan ben Gudgada's
הלכה halacha isn't obvious, but once you teach that, shouldn't this be
obvious as well? No. מהו דתימא כיון דאמר קנסי שטר חוב זה
בטולי בטליה, mahu d'teima kivan de'amar kinsi shtar chov zeh bitulei bitaleih,
no, I might think it's one thing to say what you're doing
and she didn't fully understand, you know, then we could say you
don't need her full understanding. But when he says take this שטר
חוב, shtar chov, he was calling it a promissory note, he was
implicitly nullifying its status as a גט, get, right? And we had
the whole idea of ביטול הגט. bitul haget. gap before, right, or
you could say he was he was he was reframing the meaning
of the giving. So maybe she doesn't need her awareness, but he's
reframed it or he's been מבטל mevatel it. So קמשמע לן, kamashmalan,
אם איתא דבטליה לאהדורי הוה אמר להו. im ita devatlei leadurei hava
amar lehu. No, we say if he wanted to be מבטל mevatel
it, he would have told it to the witnesses. He told the
witnesses, "I'm about to divorce my wife." So therefore, given that, you
know, he would not have done this after having told the witnesses
without updating the witnesses. So we're going to say that him saying
this is not a reframing, it is not meant to be a
ביטול. bittul. והאי דקאמר הכי משום כיסופא. vehai dekamar hachi mishum kisufa.
So then why did he say it's a שטר חוב? shtar hov?
He was embarrassed to say he's divorcing her, or maybe he just
wanted to be particularly mean. Okay, but whatever the reason is, we
use the fact that he didn't tell the עדים edim to show
that this statement is not meant to reframe or is not meant
to מבטל mevatel the גט. get. Okay, so that's fine and that's
definitely a חידוש. hiddush. You know, I would say the other חידוש
hiddush of course is that even though a חרשת hereshet is not
a בת דעת, bat da'at,
the גמרא Gemara understood that they that deaf people even when we
assume they didn't have full intellect, assume that they had a degree
of intellect. It says דעתא קלישתא da'ata kalishta in one גמרא, Gemara,
like a weakened intellect. And having a weakened intellect and not being
able to fully appreciate is still different than completely being misrepresented and
not being aware of what's going on at all. So anyway it
is an interesting גמרא, Gemara, right, and you know, raises the question:
could you give it to your wife when she's asleep? You know,
how far do you take this? We'll see about that as the
מסכת masechet continues. That's the first case. והקטנה בת ישראל, ve-haktana bat
Yisrael, second case.
A קטנה ktana who is married by her brother and mother, it's
not a דאורייתא de-Oraita marriage. She's married to a כהן kohen and
nevertheless she can eat תרומה. terumah. So what is this about? So
the גמרא Gemara first says in the process of figure out what
it's about, it wants to point out why did if we were
trying to look at דרבנן de-rabbanan marriages, why did we jump to
a case of a קטנה? ktana? We were just talking about a
חרשת. hereshet. Okay, so why didn't we give that example? An adult
חרשת hereshet also cannot דאורייתא de-Oraita be married, or חרש heresh either,
it's not they cannot do a binding transaction, but it does work
as I mentioned before, דרבנן. de-rabbanan. So as long as we were
talking about a חרשת, hereshet, why did you switch to a קטנה?
ktana? Now of course, the case started with a קטנה ktana who
was a חרשת hereshet whose father married her, so קטנה ktana is
one piece of that. But nevertheless, the גמרא Gemara thinks the חרשת
hereshet is the part, the salient thing that sticks out, and it's
significant that if we wanted to give an idea of a דרבנן
de-rabbanan marriage that can still eat תרומה, terumah, why did it go
to קטנה ktana and not stick with חרשת? hereshet? Okay, ואילו חרשת
לא אכלה. ve'ilu hereshet lo achla. It
it's implicit in the משנה Mishnah since it left the חרשת hereshet
case, that a חרשת hereshet could not eat. מאי טעמא, mai ta'ama,
why not? גזירה שמא יאכיל חרש בחרשת. gezeira shema ya'achil heresh behereshet.
So we're afraid of a case of a כהן kohen who's a
חרש heresh married to a woman who's a חרשת, hereshet, and then
in that case they'll eat תרומה. terumah. Now, now what's the problem
with that? I mean, that's a, you know, it's also a דרבנן
de-rabbanan marriage. He's a כהן, kohen, you know, he's married to her,
who who cares if one of them is a חרש heresh or
they're both חרשים, hereshim, why should that matter? And how is it
different than a קטנה? ktana? So the גמרא Gemara says וליכול, veleychol,
why not eat it? The גמרא Gemara says קטן אוכל נבלות הוא.
katan ochel neveilot hu. Worst case, it's a minor, meaning somebody who
is not obligated, who is eating something טריף. treif. תרומה terumah is
is not able to be eaten by a non-כהן kohen or somebody
who's not דאורייתא de-Oraita married to a כהן. kohen. So that may
be something that we can tolerate. Now, this is of course a
little funny because there's a whole debate about whether קטן אוכל נבלות,
katan ochel neveilot, whether if a minor is eating טריף treif food,
whether בית דין מצווים להפרישו beit din metzuvin lehafrisho or not. Does
בית דין beit din have an obligation to intervene and to stop
this from happening? Even according to the opinion that בית דין beit
din does not have an obligation, it would be a little funny
that the רבנים rabbanim would allow לכתחילה lechatchila it to happen and
say you can feed your wife this type of תרומה. terumah. So
the fact that the גמרא Gemara is thinking, "Oh this should all
be fine," is a little funny. Also you're not allowed to be
מאכיל בידיים, ma'achil beyadayim, feed with your very own hands, and you
know, maybe this would be somewhat analogous to that. But presumably what
the גמרא Gemara means is, is that since clearly there's an overriding
desire here to make this work because she's married to a כהן
kohen and there are practical reasons why we want to, even though
it's only a דרבנן de-rabbanan marriage, allow her to eat תרומה. terumah.
So since this person, either the minor of the משנה, Mishnah, we
have to get back and see why חרש heresh is different than
the minor. But since the person, whether it's a minor or whether
it's a חרש, heresh, is not obligated in מצוות, mitzvot, so that
should, even though there's a problem of קטן אוכל נבלות, katan ochel
neveilot, that should give us enough latitude to say that we're going
to treat this דרבנן de-rabbanan as a marriage and let her eat.
Okay, so basically, what's the problem? Let her eat. And the implicit
point is, and if you don't like it, then why is קטנה
ktana any better? So let's take a look what the גמרא Gemara
says. So, גזירה שמא יאכיל חרש בפיקחת. gezeira shema ya'achil heresh befike'ach.
Ah, so now we're getting to it. It says here's the difference,
and here's why it's different than a קטנה. ktana. Because in the
case of a כהן kohen who is, you know, is is not
a חרש, heresh, that's פיקח, fike'ach, like has all of his senses,
is not a חרש. heresh. Wait wait, גזירה שמא יחליפו חרש בפיקח.
G'zeira shema yachlifu cheresh b'pikayach. Ah, so now we're getting to it.
It says here's the difference and here's why it's different than a
קטן Katan than a קטנה. Katana. Because in the case of a
כהן Kohen who is not a חרש, Cheresh, that's פיקח, Pikayach, like
has all of his senses, is not a חרש, Cheresh, right, married
to a חרשת, Chereshet, that's a דרבנן D'rabbanan marriage, and the person
eating, the woman, is halachically is not obligated because of her status
as a חרשת, Chereshet, so we can tolerate that and therefore create,
allow the דרבנן D'rabbanan marriage to work and allow her to eat
because it's not, she's not violating because as a חרשת Chereshet she's
not obligated. However, says the גמרא, Gemara, that case will easily lead
to the mirror image of that. What's the mirror image of that?
A כהן Kohen who's a חרש Cheresh married to a woman who
is a who is not a חרש. Cheresh. And in that case,
in that case the person eating, the woman, is obligated in מצות.
Mitzvos. She's not a חרשת, Chereshet, she's an adult, so therefore we
cannot allow a marriage of a כהן Kohen and a non-כהן, Kohen,
you know, a כהן Kohen and a woman, one of them being
a חרש Cheresh or חרשת, Chereshet, we can't allow them that דרבנן
D'rabbanan eat תרומה, Truma, even though there's a desire to create that
to allow that דרבנן D'rabbanan marriage to let them eat תרומה Truma
for practical reasons like the קטנה Katana case. We can't allow that
case because the חרש Cheresh case will work, but the mirror image
won't, and that will be a real violation. So we have to
not allow the חרש Cheresh case at all. So how about the
קטן Katan קטנה Katana case? Okay, so by the קטנה Katana the
same thing. The קטנה Katana eating it, that's okay, she's not obligated
and therefore a דרבנן D'rabbanan we're going to make life easy and
we're going to allow it to work. And once she becomes a
גדולה Gedola halachically she'll be married. Why aren't we afraid it's going
to lead to the reverse case of a קטן Katan married to
a גדולה? Gedola? Because that type of a marriage doesn't exist. הלכה
Halacha recognizes the marriage of an adult male to an underage female,
דאורייתא D'oraisa if it's through the father, דרבנן D'rabbanan if it's through
the brothers, and there was as I said societal needs for that,
but it does not recognize at a דאורייתא D'oraisa level or דרבנן
D'rabbanan level the marriage of a minor male to an adult female.
So then therefore since the mirror image doesn't exist, we can allow
the adult male married to the minor female, the כהן, Kohen, we
can allow her to eat the תרומה Truma even though she really
halachically is not allowed. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says וליכול בתרומה
דרבנן. V'leichol b'Truma D'rabbanan. So okay, but why not back to the
חרשת Chereshet case? I understand that if it became the flip of
the of the man being the חרש Cheresh and the woman not,
that would be a real violation,
and therefore we have to say the whole thing is off-limits. But
why not let the חרשת Chereshet eat תרומה דרבנן, Truma D'rabbanan, something
that's only rabbinic תרומה, Truma, either because of whether תרומה Truma applies
nowadays or does it apply, you know, to fruit or just to
grain and so on? Let it apply for תרומה דרבנן. Truma D'rabbanan.
And therefore, you know, worst case scenario if it leads to the
flip case and it leads to a חרש Cheresh married to an
adult woman and she eats the תרומה דרבנן, Truma D'rabbanan, it'll only
be a rabbinic issue. So let's allow the חרשת Chereshet case to
work, and maybe we don't have to safeguard the flip if we're
only dealing with a דרבנן D'rabbanan issue. So the גמרא Gemara says
no, גזירה שמא אתי למיכל בתרומה דאורייתא. G'zeira shema ati l'meichal b'Truma
D'oraisa. You know, we're afraid one thing will lead to the other,
and this might sound like a גזירה לגזירה, G'zeira l'g'zeira, two safeguards,
but the reality is sometimes we do make two safeguards. So we
don't let the חרשת Chereshet eat even תרומה דרבנן Truma D'rabbanan because
even with this דרבנן D'rabbanan marriage, which would be nice, תרומה דרבנן
דרבנן Truma D'rabbanan D'rabbanan marriage and so on, so you know, they
can make all the rules because the whole thing is only תרומה
דרבנן, Truma D'rabbanan, but still even though that would be great, we
don't allow it because it could lead to her being a non-חרש,
Cheresh, him not to have him being a חרש Cheresh and lead
to a דאורייתא, D'oraisa, so two things would have to change and
that would be a real violation and therefore we have to not
allow it. But by the קטנה Katana case we can because there
doesn't exist the mirror image. רש"י Rashi does say to make the
קטנה Katana case more palpable that we're talking about תרומה דרבנן Truma
D'rabbanan even in the case of the קטנה, Katana, but you don't
necessarily get that sense in the גמרא. Gemara. In the גמרא Gemara
you get the sense even תרומה דאורייתא Truma D'oraisa since she's only
a minor we might want to allow the דרבנן D'rabbanan marriage here
to define and to allow her to eat this תרומה. Truma. Okay,
so that's the second case of a דרבנן D'rabbanan marriage and the
woman eating in the תרומה. Truma.
Okay, now it does not deal with the ירושה Yerusha case at
all and goes on to המריש הגזול שבנאו, Hamarish hagazul shebnao, the
beam that was stolen that was built into the building. תנו רבנן,
Tanu Rabbanan, our rabbis taught: גזל מריש ובנאו בבירה, Gazal marish u'bnao
b'bira,
somebody stole a beam and built it into a building. בית שמאי
אומרים: Beis Shammai omrim: מקעקע כל הבירה כולה ומחזיר מריש לבעליו. Meka'ka
kol habira kula u'machazir marish l'ba'alav. בית שמאי Beis Shammai being like
the one you got to keep to the letter of the law,
not responsive
to some of these human realities, interesting given the whole nice responsive
בית שמאי Beis Shammai we had a while ago about the עבד
Eved that was half free and half slave. Anyway, he says, I
don't care, you're a גנב, Gannav, we should not go easy on
you, you got to tear down your whole building and return it
to the owners. ובית הלל אומרים: U'Beis Hillel omrim: אין לו אלא
דמי מריש בלבד. Ein lo ela d'mei marish bilvad. No,
the owner only can demand the cost of the beam. משום mishum
תקנת השבים, takanat hashavim.
in order to make it more possible for people to do תשובה,
Teshuva, not to create obstacles for people to own up to their
actions. Okay. And now והחטאת הגזולה, ve'ha-chatas ha-gezula, the stolen חטאת, chatas,
as again I said the language in the משנה Mishnah was a
little vague: did you steal the actual animal that, you know, when
ראובן Reuven stole שמעון's Shimon's sacrifice of שמעון, Shimon, did he steal
something שמעון Shimon had sanctified? Or did he steal just an animal
of שמעון's Shimon's and he sanctified it? Now, if שמעון Shimon had
already sanctified it, there's no question, nothing could even begin to be
a beginning conversation. It's שמעון's Shimon's חטאת, chatas, the קדושה kedushah it
has is connected to שמעון, Shimon, and therefore there would be no
question it wouldn't work. The question and what we're going to deal
with is he stole שמעון's Shimon's animal, ראובן Reuven did, and then
ראובן Reuven sanctified it. So, did he get enough ownership over that
animal by stealing it and then by sanctifying it that that actually
makes it his and that for it actually does work as ראובן's
Reuven's חטאת? chatas? That's the question. Okay. The משנה Mishnah says it
doesn't work if it is not well known, not, you know, public
knowledge, but let's figure out what the real הלכה halacha should be
before we get into any תקנה. takanah.
אמר עולא, Amar Ulla, says עולא, Ulla, דבר תורה בין נודע בין
לא נודע אינה מכפרת. d'var Torah ben noda ben lo noda eina
mechaperes. The real הלכה halacha before you get to any תקנה takanah
is whether this was known, a publicly known that this was stolen.
If ראובן Reuven steals שמעון's Shimon's animal and sanctifies it, it's not
going to work for שמעון. Shimon. For ראובן. Reuven. Why not? מאי
טעמא יאוש כדי לא קני. mai taama yeiush k'dei lo kani. Let's
assume that as soon as it's stolen, and גזילה gezeilah by the
way is like a robbery, not burglary, it's publicly known, like it's
known that it was stolen. The owner finds out, it was maybe
stolen directly from him, and therefore there's a whole debate in the
גמרא בבבא קמא, Gemara in Bava Kamma, but עולא Ulla is saying
let's assume we can automatically assume the owner knows about it and
the owner is מייאש, m'yaesh, gives up hope of ever getting it
back. That's יאוש. yeiush. So there's a debate in the גמרא בבבא
קמא Gemara in Bava Kamma whether יאוש yeiush is קונה. koneh. After
the owner has given up hope of getting it back, does that
mean that the גזלן gazlan owns it? Now, clear,
there are cases where we know יאוש yeiush works. A classic example
of יאוש yeiush is not by גזילה, gezeilah, but it starts with
a lost object. I lost my wallet in Grand Central Station, I
said, 'Oh, my God, I'm never going to get it back, forget
about it,' I've given up hope, and then somebody finds it. If
they can assume that I knew about it and therefore that there
was יאוש, yeiush, then they can keep it. Why? Because once I
gave up hope, then that makes it free, like I no longer
have my connection to it, it's no longer sort of under my
control, even psychologically, and therefore it's free for them to take and
take it into their control. That's called יאוש ושינוי רשות. yeiush v'shinui
reshus. What happens by the גזלן gazlan is different though. By the
גזלן, gazlan, first ראובן Reuven has it, he's in his possession, and
then I have given up hope. ראובן Reuven doesn't take it from
being out in the middle of Grand Central Station, he was holding
on to it while I gave up hope. He might not be
entitled now to say, 'Oh, so דב Dov isn't tot- conceptually, you
know, psychologically holding on to it, now it's free for me to
take.' No, he took it when it was totally under my control.
He has an obligation to return it to me. My יאוש yeiush
doesn't work for him. Maybe if he sold it to somebody, it
would work for that next guy, but my יאוש yeiush doesn't work
for him. He took it from me, he's got to return it
to me. So that's the question whether יאוש כדי yeiush k'dei by
itself without שינוי רשות shinui reshus in the hands of the גזלן,
gazlan, does יאוש yeiush work? So עולא Ulla says, look, יאוש yeiush
by itself does not work. And therefore ראובן Reuven stole שמעון's Shimon's
cow, this cow does not belong to ראובן. Reuven. He is not
the owner of it, even with יאוש. yeiush. And therefore, what, therefore
when he sanctifies it, it doesn't really become his קרבן. korban. Now,
you gotta pause for a moment because it'll be interesting when we
flip the גמרא. Gemara. The simplest way to say it is flip
the page. When he sanctifies it, it's not his, so you can't
sanctify something that's not yours. So he's calling it a חטאת, chatas,
but it's really not a חטאת chatas at all, it's just a
cow.
However, there is another possibility, and this emerges from comparing this גמרא
Gemara to other גמרות, Gemaras, and which is that when he sanctifies
it, that becomes the שינוי רשות. shinui reshus. Now it's like הקדש
hekdesh takes possession of it, or it becomes a שינוי השם. shinui
hashem. Now its identity changes and it's called a קרבן. korban. And
the יאוש yeiush and his physical possession of it might give him
enough traction, enough ownership, even though he doesn't fully own it, in
order to hand it over to הקדש hekdesh by his הקדש, hekdesh,
or in order to change its status. So it could be that
it actually is a חטאת, chatas, it is sanctified. But since it
came through theft, when it got- when it went into הקדש, hekdesh,
it was still stolen, he didn't own it yet. So since he
didn't own it yet at the moment he sanctified it, it does
not work for him. Basically, based on the principle of מצוה הבאה
בעבירה, mitzvah haba'ah b'aveirah, since it came through the sin and it
was not his when he sanctified it, even if it right now
is קדוש, kadosh, it still would not work. So one way or
another, since he did not own it, it's either not even a
קרבן korban or certainly not a קרבן korban that works for him.
The basic הלכה halacha says עולא Ulla is this קרבן korban does
not work. Okay, ומה טעם אמרו לא נודע מכפרת? uma ta'am amru
lo noda mechapperes?
So why did they say that if it's not public knowledge, it
will work, it will atone for ראובן Reuven and ראובן Reuven now
does not have to bring another קרבן? korban? שלא יהו כהנים עצבים,
shelo yehu kohanim atzeivim, so the כהנים kohanim should not be anguished,
the כהנים kohanim should not feel like, oh my god, you know,
we found out afterwards that this guy had stolen this קרבן korban
and now you know, or look, every day we're taking קרבנות korbanos
from sinners, so you know, okay, and שוגג, shogeg, whatever, but who
knows, you know, maybe we're going to eat some stuff that might
be stolen and then we will if since it wasn't really sanctified,
forget just that it didn't work for him and whether he's obligated
in a קרבן, korban, we ate stuff that you know that like
that wasn't kosher essentially, okay, we ate a you know so
you know חולין chullin that was שחט shechted in the בית המקדש
Beis Hamikdash or קרבן korban that was שחט shechted that didn't work,
you're not allowed to eat that stuff if it's not מכפר. mechapper.
So in order that the כהנים kohanim shouldn't worry about this beforehand
or afterwards if it got found out, we're saying you know what,
it doesn't matter, we're going to say that it works, okay, and
and you don't have to bring another one. Now and but of
course if it's known, if it was public knowledge, we don't want
you to be a party to that and we don't want to
come and help you in that case. If it's public knowledge you
have to not accept it,
okay? נמצא מזבח בטל. nimtza mizbe'ach batel. So if the כהנים kohanim
were afraid about accepting קרבנות korbanos from people, they would not bring
you know the קרבנות korbanos would not be brought. So therefore that
was the... okay I'm sorry excuse me I skipped a line. אמרי
ליה רבנן, amrei lei rabanan, the rabbis said no so שלא יהו
כהנים עצבים, shelo yehu kohanim atzeivim, אמרי ליה רבנן amrei lei rabanan
so the rabbis said to him to עולא, Ulla, ואנן מפני תיקון
המזבח תנן, va'anan mipnei tikkun hamizbe'ach tnan, but it says because of
the sake of the מזבח, mizbe'ach, you're saying it's for the sake
of the כהנים? kohanim? So the answer is אמר להם, amar lahem,
כיון דכהנים עצבים נמצא מזבח בטל. keivan de-kohanim atzeivim nimtza mizbe'ach batel.
If the כהנים kohanim are anguished and sad then that's going to
impact them, their eagerness to do their work and they'll maybe have
to triple check everything before they accept it and so on and
it's going to have an impact on the מזבח. mizbe'ach. We want
things to go smoothly. If it's known you shouldn't accept it, but
otherwise it's okay. Now of course you know תוספות Tosafos discusses the
whole question about how can the חכמים chachamim or רש"י Rashi also
whatever, how can the חכמים chachamim tell you you don't have to
bring a קרבן korban if you're still obligated in a קרבן korban
if it really didn't work, you know and that's about the ability
of חכמים chachamim to say to you know to be override תורה
Torah when it comes to like שב ואל תעשה, shev v'al ta'aseh,
to like passively not do something. You know also an interesting question
again what exactly is the status of the קרבן, korban, is it
חולין שנשחטו בעזרה? chullin shenishchetu ba'azarah? You know is that דאורייתא de-Oraisa
or not? What exactly are the הלכות halachos there or maybe it
wasn't חולין, chullin, maybe it really was a קרבן korban just a
קרבן korban that didn't work. But anyway דרבנן de-rabanan we're going to
say that it worked, דאורייתא de-Oraisa none of this should work. Okay
that's עולא. Ulla. רב
יהודה אמר, Rav Yehuda amar, now רב יהודה Rav Yehuda said, דבר
תורה בין נודע בין לא נודע מכפר. devar Torah bein noda bein
lo noda mechapper. No, no, no, מעיקר הדין me'ikar hadin it works
either way, okay, even if it was well known. מאי טעמא? mai
ta'ama? יאוש כדי קני, ye'ush kadeh konei, because יאוש ye'ush does work.
So as soon as he stole שמעון Shimon's cow, it's his cow.
And שמעון Shimon gave up hope. Now he sanctified it, it was
already his when he sanctified it, so it's totally ראובן Reuven's חטאת,
chatas, totally should work. Okay, ומה טעם אמרו uma ta'am amru so
then why did they say נודע אינה מכפרת, noda einah mechapperess, that
if it's a public knowledge it doesn't work? שלא יאמרו מזבח אוכל
גזילות. shelo yomru mizbe'ach ochel gezeilos. Because you don't want to say,
look, you know, things that are publicly stolen being offered up on
the מזבח. mizbe'ach. Look at this מזבח, mizbe'ach, it's eating, it's consuming
stolen, you know, stolen goods, right? It makes the כהנים kohanim and
the מזבח mizbe'ach and everybody complicit in the theft here. You know,
go ahead and steal, we don't care, just bring us a קרבן.
korban. It's horrific in terms of what it's modeling. The whole גמרא
gemara about מצווה הבאה בעבירה, mitzvah haba'ah ba'aveirah, you know, starts with
a פסוק pasuk of שונא גזל בעולה, sonei gezel b'olah, I ה'
Hashem hate something stolen in a burnt offering. Right? You know that's
where you have to start by modeling, you don't think that you
get to make up for it for stealing by putting it on
the מזבח. mizbe'ach. Okay so we really have to make sure that
if it's known that it's stolen we are not going to accept
it. Alright so that's the הלכה. halacha. So now the גמרא gemara
says like this, בשלמא לעולא היינו דקתני חטאת. bishlama le-Ulla hainu de-ktani
chatas. So according to עולא Ulla I understand, so for עולא Ulla
remember the חידוש chiddush is that we are going to say it
shouldn't work but the חידוש chiddush is we're going to let it
work. So that's why we said a חטאת, chatas, okay why why
does that make sense because the concern is that the כהנים kohanim
didn't want to feel that they were eating something that wasn't really
a קרבן, korban, okay so therefore you have to give the only
things that the כהנים kohanim really eat, the שלמים shelamim the owner
eat, the עולה olah goes all on the מזבח, mizbe'ach, so the
concern is the חטאת, chatas, okay חטאת chatas and an אשם asham
but whatever we understand why it's חטאת, chatas, it's about the כהנים.
kohanim. אלא לרב יהודה מאי איריא חטאת אפילו עולה נמי לא. ela
le-Rav Yehuda mai irya chatas, afilu olah nami lo. But according to
רב יהודה Rav Yehuda why mention a חטאת, chatas, even an עולה,
olah, you know an עולה olah even all the more so should
be a problem, the whole thing is being consumed as I said,
the פסוק pasuk says אני ה' שונא גזל בעולה. ani Hashem sonei
gezel b'olah. So מאי איריא אפילו עולה נמי mai irya afilu olah
nami excuse me, so the גמרא gemara says לא מיבעיא קאמר. lo
mibaya ka'amar. Yeah, yeah, of course, it goes without saying. לא מיבעיא
עולה דכליל היא, lo mibaya olah de-kalil hi, of course it goes
without saying that we're not going to let that an עולה *olah*
work, cause that's really like the whole thing going up to God,
and that's something that's going to be stolen. I mean, that really
is, you know,
is horrific what that is modeling. That God is taking this stolen
sacrifice and it's being offered up to God. דכולה כליל היא *d'kulla
kalil hi*, אלא אפילו חטאת Chatas, נמי דחלב ודם הוא דסליק לגבי
מזבח *ella afillu chatas nami decheilev vadam hu desalik legabei mizbeach*. But
a חטאת *chatas* where the כהנים *kohanim* eat the meat, and the
only thing you really put on the מזבח *mizbeach* is blood and
the fat, that type of a thing, wouldn't so much look that
we're able to put our stolen stuff on the מזבח *mizbeach*. Didn't
really go on the מזבח *mizbeach*, it's only the כהנים *kohanim* who
ate it, maybe it won't look so bad. Okay, so אפילו הכי
גזר שלא יהא מזבח אוכל נבילות וגזילות *afillu hachi gazar shelo yehei
mizbeach ochel neveilot u'gezeilot*. Even so, they said no, it still looks
like the מזבח *mizbeach* is eating stolen things. It still makes it
horrific that people think they can steal and then bring it as
a קרבן Korban *korban*. And then of course the irony is bring
it as a קרבן Korban, *korban* as a חטאת *chatas* and then
they think it'll atone for them, so we have to make a
policy that we are not going to accept it. Okay, fine. So
now we have two ways of understanding. One is it shouldn't work,
but we're going to let it work, and the other is it
does work, but we're going to not let it work. Now there's
a question in that approach that we're going to not let it
work, which is how far does that go? Does that mean we
refuse to accept it? Yes, obviously. What if we accepted it, this
well-known, this publicly known גזילה *gezeilah*, we accepted it and put it
on the מזבח *mizbeach* and sprinkled the blood? Are we going to
tell the owner that he now has to bring—oh, you know what?
It didn't work. You have to go ahead and bring another קרבן
Korban. *korban*. Right? Or maybe that far we won't go, because that
will really be like a חולין *chullin*, you know, bringing חולין *chullin*
on the מזבח *mizbeach*. So there're definitely, you know, so there're definitely
those that say that that far we would not go if it
was already brought, you know, that would be okay. Although again, the
language of the משנה mishna, *Mishnah* of אינה מכפרת *einah mechaperet* does
not exactly sound that way. The language of the משנה mishna. *Mishnah*
says—excuse me, the משנה mishnah *Mishnah* was talking about the לא נודע
*lo noda* as מכפרת *mechaperet*. So okay, it could still work. All
right, so that's the question about when it is known how far
are we going to go, even בדיעבד *bedi'avad* that it was offered
or only to refuse to accept it to begin with?
Let's take a look now as the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* continues.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this, תנן חטאת הגזולה
שלא נודעה לרבים היא מכפרת *tenan chatas hagezulah shelo noda'ah lerabbim hi
mechaperet*. So the משנה *Mishnah* says that תקנה Takana *takanah* was if
it is stolen and it is not well known that it atones.
So who does that sound like? So that's pretty much—מפני תיקון המזבח
*mipnei tikkun hamizbeach*. בשלמא לעולא ניחא *bishlama l'Ulla nicha*, that works perfectly
for עולא Ulla, *Ulla*. The תקנה Takana *takanah* is that we will
let it
atone if it's not known, גזולה שאינה נודעה לרבים *gezulah she'einah noda'ah
lerabbim* that we will let it atone. אלא לרב יהודה איפכא מיבעי
ליה *ella l'Rav Yehuda ipcha miba'ei lei*. But according to רב יהודה
*Rav Yehuda*, it should have said the opposite, the תקנה Takana *takanah*
was that when it was known to be stolen, it won't work.
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, הכי נמי קאמר *hachi nami ka'amar*.
You're right, that is really implicitly what it's saying. לא נודע מכפרת,
נודע—excuse me—לא נודע מכפרת, נודע אינה מכפרת מפני תיקון המזבח *lo noda
mechaperet, noda einah mechaperet mipnei tikkun hamizbeach*. That what they said was
if it's not well known, meaning only if it's not well known
will it work. Implicitly, when it is a publicly known, then it
won't work because of תיקון המזבח *tikkun hamizbeach*. All right, so it's
a little funny why it would sort of bury the lead, but
anyway, that's how he's reading it. Clearly, the simple read of the
משנה *Mishnah* is like עולא Ulla *Ulla*, that the תקנה Takana *takanah*
is that it—that it does work even though it shouldn't. Okay, מתיב
רבא Rava *metiv Rava*. Now רבא *Rava* challenge. Here we have a
משנה *Mishnah*. גנב והקדיש ואחר כך טבח ומכר *ganav vehikdish v'achar kach
tavach umachar*. Exactly our case. ראובן Reuven *Reuven* stole this animal from
שמעון *Shimon*, a cow, and then he slaughtered it or sold it,
and the normal הלכה Halacha *halachah* is that if you steal a
cow or sheep and you slaughter it or you sell it, that
you have to pay four or five depending on cow or sheep.
So that's what he did. He slaughtered and sold it. משלם תשלומי
כפל ואינו משלם תשלומי ארבע וחמישה *meshalem tashlumei khefel v'eino meshalem tashlumei
arba vechamishah*. He pays double for being a גנב *ganav*, for having
stolen it, but he does not pay four and five. Why does
he not pay four and five? Because after he sanctified it, it
was no longer his. And therefore, he was, you know, it belonged
to הקדש *hekdesh*. It no longer belonged to שמעון *Shimon*. It became
sanctified and went out totally out of שמעון *Shimon*'s control. And therefore,
you're not חייב Chayav *chayav* if you slaughter it or sell it
after the original owner no longer owns it. Okay, so משלם תשלומי
כפל ואינו משלם תשלומי ארבע וחמישה *meshalem tashlumei khefel v'eino meshalem tashlumei
arba vechamishah*. ותני עלה בחוץ כהאי גוונא ענוש כרת Kares *vetani alah
bachutz kehai gavna anush kares*. But we taught if he went now
after he sanctified this to bring it as a קרבן Korban *korban*
outside of the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash? *Beit Hamikdash*, then he would
be חייב Chayav כרת Kares. *chayav kares*. That's שחוטי חוץ *shichutei chutz*,
bringing something sanctified as a קרבן Korban *korban* outside the בית המקדש
Beis Hamikdash. *Beit Hamikdash*. Now we've got a problem. What's our problem?
The only thing that you're חייב Chayav כרת Kares *chayav kares* for
when you bring as a קרבן Korban *korban* outside the בית המקדש
Beis Hamikdash, *Beit Hamikdash* is something that could be brought as an
acceptable קרבן Korban, *korban* in the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash? *Beit Hamikdash*.
So this sounds like stealing it and sanctifying it—if you're now חייב
Chayav *chayav* if you bring it as a קרבן *korban* out of
the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash *Beit Hamikdash*—sounds like מעיקר הדין *me'ikar hadin*
it would work as a קרבן *korban* in the בית המקדש Beis
Hamikdash, *Beit Hamikdash*, otherwise you wouldn't be חייב Chayav *chayav* outside. That
proves like רב יהודה *Rav Yehuda* and against עולא Ulla? *Ulla*. ואי
אמרת יאוש Yiush כדי לא קני *v'ei amrat ye'ush k'dei lo kani*,
and if you say like עולא Ulla *Ulla* that יאוש *ye'ush* alone
did not work, so
כרת Kares, מאי Mai? עבידתיה *kares mai avidteih*?
And even if, for example, we'll say that it wasn't well known,
but it doesn't work according מדאורייתא. Mid'oraita, So since it doesn't work
מדאורייתא, only דרבנן Derabbanan we're pretending as if it works according to
עולא, Ulla. then how can you explain why it works outside, why
you're חייב כרת Kares. outside of the בית
המקדש? Beis Hamikdash So אמר רב שיזבי, Amar Rav Shizbi, כרת מדבריהם.
Kares Midivreihem. No, דרבנן Derabbanan you have כרת. Kares. When we said
כרת Kares? we didn't really mean כרת, Kares. we really meant we'll
pretend דרבנן Derabbanan like you have כרת. Kares Okay, so the גמרא
Gemara says אחיכו עליה, Achiku Alei, people laughed on them in response.
כרת מדבריהם מי איכא? Kares Midivreihem Mi Ika? We never speak about
דרבנן Derabbanan כרת. Kares. We can speak about דרבנן Derabbanan lashes because
we actually give you lashes. We could think about something being דרבנן
Derabbanan forbidden because actually we are saying it's forbidden and if you
listen to the rabbis, you follow our rules. But how do you
speak about דרבנן Derabbanan כרת? Kares. That's a metaphysical reality. We don't
create דרבנן Derabbanan כרת. Kares. So that can't be the answer. When
we say כרת Kares we have to really mean כרת. Kares So
the גמרא Gemara says אמר להו רבא, Amar Lehu Rava, so רבא
responded back to the rabbis that laughed. גברא רבה אמר מילתא לא
תחיכו עליה. Gavra Rabba Amar Milta Lo Techechu Alei. A great person
said something. Even if it sounds silly to you, don't laugh. Presumably
there's something behind it. כרת על ידי דבריהם בא לו. Kares Al
Yedei Divreihem Ba Lo. What he meant to say was, whether he
really meant it or not is not the point, that he means
that through a דרבנן Derabbanan edict you wind up getting דאורייתא De'oraisa
כרת. Kares. It's not a דרבנן Derabbanan כרת. Kares. It's a כרת
Kares that came because of what the rabbis did. Now, how did
כרת Kares come because of what the rabbis did? He's going to
tell you. ואוקמוה רבנן ברשותיה כי היכי דליחייב עליה. Ve'okmuha Rabbanan Birshusei
Ki Heichi Delichayev Alei. The rabbis made you own it in order
that you should be חייב if you were to שחיטה Shecht it
out of the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. Now, that sounds a little
bit like you went ahead, you sanctified this, you שחיטה Shechted it
outside of the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash? retroactively we're going to say
you owned it when you sanctified it in order because now we
want to get you כרת. That seems a little convoluted. So תוספות
Tosfos says much simpler than that what he really means is the
following. At the moment you sanctified it, if we're dealing with a
קרבן that was not publicly known that this was stolen, so remember
what will be the הלכה Halacha if you bring it to the
בית המקדש? Beis Hamikdash. According to עולא Ulla. the הלכה Halacha? is
we're going to want this to work. If it's not publicly known,
it really shouldn't work, but we're going to want it to work.
So how did we make that happen according to עולא? That this
stolen animal works even though it shouldn't? So you could just say
we just said it worked and don't bother bringing another one. But
there's a better way. We could actually make it work. We could
say that moment that you're sanctifying it, דרבנן Derabbanan now we are
making you own it. The rabbis have the right to assign ownership.
So what this is saying is when עולא said that תקנה Takana
was that it's going to work if it's not publicly known, what
the תקנה takana. actually did was it meant if you sanctify this
animal you stole and you sanctified as a קרבן, as a חטאת,
we're going to make it yours a second before you sanctified it.
Now when it's sanctified, it's a hundred percent a כשר Kosher קרבן.
And now when you bring it, it'll work if you bring it
in the בית המקדש and if you bring it out of the
בית המקדש, you'll be חייב כרת. Okay, so that explains how this
whole thing works according to עולא. And by the way, we should
say that it's important to note going back to this issue about
does it really become sanctified or not, you know in this יאוש
ושינוי רשות, Yiush Veshenui Reshus, that the גמרא Gemara was not bothered
by the idea of four and five. It was only bothered about
the question of whether it works for him as a קרבן out
of the בית המקדש or in the בית המקדש. The fact that
you're exempt from four or five, the גמרא gemara was okay with
עולא. Even though יאוש didn't work, when you sanctified it, that sanctity
actually did work and you're not חייב now if you sell it
or slaughter it, four and five, it really isn't yours anymore. But
because it wasn't yours when you sanctified it, it won't work as
a קרבן and the question was and therefore how is the תקנה
going to mean that you're going to be חייב כרת out of
the בית המקדש? And the answer is yes, the תקנה will mean
that because the תקנה made you own it before you sanctified it.
And that's why it's going to work as a קרבן and that's
why it's going to work for כרת out of the בית המקדש.
So the גמרא gemara, says like this, כי היכי דליחייב עליה. Ki
Heichi Delichayev Alei. אמר רבא הא ודאי קמיבעיא ליה. Amar Rava Ha
Vadai Kamibaya Lei. This is the question that I have. דאוקמוה רבנן
ברשותיה משעת גניבה או משעת הקדש? De'okmuha Rabbanan Birshusei Mishas Gneiva O
Mishas Hekdesh? Now
I've already been giving you the answer. But when the rabbis said
you owned it, did they say you owned it from the moment
you stole it or from the moment you sanctified it or a
second before you sanctified it? So the גמרא says למאי נפקא מינה,
Lemai Nafaka Mina, what would be the difference? לגיזותיה ולולדותיה. Ligizoseha Uvladoseha.
Let's say it improved in value from the moment you stole it.
You held on to it for a year before you sanctified it
and you sheared it and it gave birth to some babies. So
if you owned it from the moment you stole it, all of
that is yours. If you only owned it the second before you
sanctified it, all of that if and when God willing you do
תשובה, Teshuvah, all of that goes back to the owners. Okay, מאי?
What's the הלכה? halacha הדר אמר רבא מסתברא משעת הקדש. Hadar Amar
Rava Mistabra Mishas Hekdesh. It makes sense a minute before you sanctified
it. שלא יהא חוטא נשכר, Shelo Yehei Chotei Niskar, we won't want
the sinner to benefit. Even if we have to make you own
it in order so that it works as a קרבן, why should
we make you own it any earlier than we absolutely have to?
Of course, what you could also say is that maybe we won't
have to make you own it at all if you never wind
up sanctifying it. Why should we across the board make you own
it? So it makes a lot of sense that what we will
say is at the moment you sanctify it, at that moment, that's
when you own it. Okay, so that is the end of those
תקנות, takanos, no really תיקון עולם, tikkun olam, but תקנת מזבח, takanas
mizbeiach, תקנת השבים, takanas hashavim, and so on. Okay, now we are
going to do another תקנה. לא היה סיקריקון ביהודה בהרוגי מלחמה. Lo
haya sikrikon bi-Yehuda be-harugei milchama.
The law of the סיקריקון, sikrikon, סיקריקון sikrikon were people that were
basically threatened to murder Jews, these were non-Jews, Romans or whatever, who
threatened to murder Jews unless they would sell them their land. Okay,
and we'll see in a minute in the משנה, special הלכות halachos
that apply there
about whether they recognize the ownership of the סיקריקון sikrikon when the
Jew was forced to sell it under that type of duress. So
the law of the סיקריקון sikrikon did not apply
at the time when they actually
were right now in the three weeks, as we teach this דף,
daf, and the whole גמרא we're going to get into is the
classic אגדתא aggadata חורבן הבית churban habayis and based on this משנה.
So and this is saying that this idea that they would steal
this land by threat of death in Judea and so on, when
it was actually the period of the war itself and people were
being slaughtered during the war,
the law of סיקריקון sikrikon did not apply. Okay, meaning it was
basically so basically we just consider well we'll see in the גמרא,
I won't ruin the surprise. Okay, מהרוגי מלחמה ואילך, Me-harugei milchama ve-eilach,
after the in the immediate aftermath of the war, when the slaughter
stopped, and still though these people were coming and threatening us and
threatening the Jews to sell their land, at that moment they said
יש בסיקריקון, yesh ba-sikrikon, the law of סיקריקון sikrikon applies. What's the
law of סיקריקון? sikrikon? So the law of סיקריקון sikrikon is the
following: כיצד לקח מסיקריקון וחזר ולקח מבעל הבית מקחו בטל. keitzad? Lakach
mi-sikrikon ve-chazar ve-lakach mi-balabayis, mikcho batel.
So basically, this סיקריקון sikrikon came and forced ראובן Reuven to sell
him his plot of land, and believe me ראובן Reuven probably sold
it at a significant discount. Now, I'm going to come and I
want to buy that plot of land. Who should we consider to
be the true owner? So the original הלכה was that we would
consider ראובן Reuven to be the true owner. And because we consider
ראובן Reuven, to be the true owner, it matters the order in
which I try to purchase it. I'm going to try to do
the right thing and buy it off of ראובן, Reuven but also
I have to pay the סיקריקון sikrikon as well. He stole it
and if I want to practically have control of the land, I'm
going to have to pay him as well. So now it depends
the order in which I'm going to go about that. So לקח
מסיקריקון וחזר ולקח מבעל הבית, Lakach mi-sikrikon ve-chazar ve-lakach mi-balabayis, if first
I paid the סיקריקון sikrikon and then I went to ראובן Reuven
and got ראובן Reuven to sell it to me, מקחו בטל. mikcho
batel. That doesn't work. Because the only reason ראובן Reuven is agreeing
to sell it to me is because he
figures what's the סיקריקון sikrikon going to do if he finds out
that ראובן Reuven isn't giving up all of his rights? The סיקריקון
sikrikon basically put a gun to ראובן's Reuven head, said sell me
the land, ראובן Reuven. sold him the land. Now the סיקריקון sikrikon
is selling it to me. And now I'm going to try to
buy it to ראובן. Reuven If ראובן Reuven doesn't go along with
it, he's going to get serious grief from this סיקריקון sikrikon because
he's holding things up
and gumming up the whole works. So in that case, that doesn't
work. We don't really believe ראובן Reuven, really wanted to sell it
to me, I should not be in cahoots with
this סיקריקון. sikrikon. Okay, so מבעל הבית וחזר ולקח מסיקריקון, Mi-balabayis ve-chazar
ve-lakach mi-sikrikon, however, if first I went to ראובן, Reuven and then
ראובן Reuven was under no pressure to sell it to me, and
ראובן Reuven had a deal with a bad situation, this סיקריקון sikrikon
stole his land, he had no idea if he was ever going
to get it back, he could freely decide Dov, if you think
you can manage to go ahead and get it, or you have
enough money to pay the סיקריקון sikrikon something whatever, געזונטערהייט, gezunterheit, at
least I'm going to salvage something from it and I will sell
my rights to you, I will sell it to you for X
amount. In that case, he sold it to me totally
freely, so וחזר ולקח מסיקריקון מקחו קיים, ve-chazar ve-lakach mi-sikrikon mikcho kayam,
so that would work. Okay, now similarly, לקח מן האיש וחזר ולקח
מן האישה מקחו בטל. Lakach min ha-ish ve-chazar ve-lakach min ha-isha mikcho
batel. Let's say I want to buy property that belongs to the
wife in the marriage, but it's under the husband's control. Either she
brought it in in her dowry, or the husband or she has
a lien on it against her כתובה, ksuva, but it's some property
that is fundamentally
the wife is the one with rights, sort of like ראובן in
the other story, but the husband is the one who's in control
of it, like the סיקריקון. sikrikon. All right, so in that case,
I mean obviously that's a bad analogy, but you get the idea.
Okay, the question is whether we assume both parties are doing it
willingly. So לקח מן האיש וחזר ולקח מן האישה מקחו בטל. Lakach
min ha-ish ve-chazar ve-lakach min ha-isha mikcho batel. If first I got
the husband to sell me his rights in this property and then
I went to the wife, that doesn't work. Because the wife might
not really want to do it, but she wants to do it
because she doesn't want to get grief from her husband. Okay, so
she's going along even though she doesn't really want to. מן האישה
וחזר ולקח מן האיש, min ha'ishah vechazar velakach min ha'ish, first I
went to the wife and then I went to the husband, in
that case nobody was compelling the woman to first sell me her
rights to the property, so in that case המכר קיים, hamakher kayam,
it worked. זו משנה ראשונה. zo mishnah rishonah. This was the first
teaching. בית דין beis din של אחריהם אמרו, shel achreihem amru, but
the a later בית דין beis din ruled, הלקוח מ- halokeach mi-
so the first ruling of the law of the סיקריקון sikrikon was
we do not recognize the ownership of the סיקריקון, sikrikon, Reuven is
the real owner, and whether Reuven is freely selling it or not,
whether we deem him to be freely selling it, depends on whether
you went first to Reuven or first to the סיקריקון. sikrikon. Okay,
but Reuven was recognized as the real owner. What did the later
בית דין beis din say? הלקוח מסיקריקון נותן לבעלים רביע. halokeach misikrikon
nosein libaalim revia. That if you buy it that they real- that
if you buy it from the סיקריקון, sikrikon, you don't have to
worry about Reuven. Okay, in practice we're going to assume we're going
to treat the סיקריקון sikrikon as the
owner and but because we're also going to assume though that the
סיקריקון sikrikon was able to buy it at a twenty-five percent discount
from Reuven. That's pretty impressive that or whatever unimpressive that he was
only able to get a twenty-five percent discount with a gun to
Reuven's head. But maybe because you know it was the implied use
of force or whatever and wanted and it was still to some
degree wanted to make it look legit. So anyway he only got
it at a twenty-five percent discount from Reuven. So in that case
the only thing Reuven really lost out, well, he might not have
wanted to sell the field, but dollars and cents what he lost
out was the twenty-five percent. So therefore in practice now that these
סיקריקוןs sikrikon have this land and are we really going to continue
to treat Reuven as the owner and then have to try to
buy it from both of them? You know, then it's going to
be anyway that's going to be really impossible to try to get
it back under Jewish control. You're going to have to pay a
lot to the סיקריקון sikrikon and a lot to Reuven. So in
practice it's a lot easier to work for function as real- as
seeing the סיקריקון sikrikon as the true owner and just going ahead
and giving Reuven the amount that Reuven lost out on the transaction,
the twenty-five percent that he lost out. So that was the new
ruling. הלקוח מסיקריקון נותן לבעלים רביע. halokeach misikrikon nosein libaalim revia. אימתי,
eimasai, when is this true? בזמן שאין בידם ליקח. bizman she'ein beyadam
likach. If Reuven does not have the wherewithal to purchase it. אבל
יש בידם ליקח הם קודמין לכל אדם. aval yeish beyadam likach heim
kodmin lechol adam. But if Reuven can buy it back, then they
also have to be given the preference. Okay, so this was very
pragmatic. As opposed to say technically Reuven owns it, you gotta buy
off the סיקריקון sikrikon and then you gotta buy it from Reuven
and you gotta do it in the right order, we just say
let's just deal with the facts on the ground. Okay? The סיקריקון
sikrikon has it. We're not going to fix that situation. What we
can do is we can say, first of all, Reuven gets first
right to buy it before anybody else. And second of all, if
you buy it from the סיקריקון, sikrikon, you have an obligation to
pay Reuven what he lost in the transaction, the twenty-five percent that
he lost out. Okay? Now, רבי הושיב בית דין ונמנו, rabbi hoshib
beis din venimnu, Rabbi convened a בית דין beis din and they
voted. שהתה בפני סיקריקון שנים עשר חודש כל הקודם ליקח זכה. shehasah
bifnei sikrikon shenayim asar chodesh kol hakodem likach zachah. אבל נותן לבעלים
רביע. aval nosein libaalim revia. That if it stayed within the hands
of the סיקריקון sikrikon for twelve months, then first come first serve,
meaning that then it sounds like that Reuven then loses his right
of, you know, he has a right of first refusal but it's
only for a year. After that point we can't start looking around
for Reuven and worrying about him. Again, we have to be practical
about this. And again maybe we also wanted to make it easy
to bring that property back under Jewish control. Okay? But the law
that you still have to give Reuven the quarter that he lost
out, the twenty-five percent he lost out, that still applies. Okay? So
we will end with this here and we will pick up tomorrow
first analyzing the משנה and then getting on to the אגדתא aggadata
that's very appropriate for this time of year about חורבן הבית. churban
habayis.